one way to represent the sum of the
first n positive integers is with a
triangular array of squares where the
first row has one square and the bottom
row has n squares then we can cut this
triangular array with this diagonal
creating one large triangle and N small
one by one triangles therefore the sum
of the first n positive integers is
given by the area of all these triangles
together the large triangle has an area
of one half N squared and each of the
small triangles has an area of one-half
giving a total combined area of one-half
n therefore the sum of the first n
positive integers is one half N squared
plus one half n